So much is happening in the world of AI
dev maybe in the last four or five
months is the acceptance that knowledge
and intelligence are not the same. All
these models are becoming very
intelligent. But what we also see is
that to be a great and powerful [music]
developer is truly AI native and is 100x
productive a lot of it comes down to
context. A way that a developer wants
[music] to write code an LLM can very
often provide a correct answer back to a
user. But if it's not the correct answer
that a user wants to see in a way that
they want to see it, it creates
frustrations.
>> The fact that you need to review in the
first place is a big limiting factor in
how productive you can be. The more you
can say upfront and trust that it will
be applied, the more you can delegate
and the more successful you can do that.
You want agents to use your software.
You want them to use your tools. You
want them to use them correctly. And
context is often times the means that
you have it. I would predict that in
2026 we'll see much more substantial use
of open models especially in development
and in recurring activities.
Before we jump into this episode, I
wanted to let you know that this podcast
is for developers building with AI at
the core. So whether that's exploring
the latest tools, the workflows, or the
best practices, this podcast's for you.
A really quick ask. 90% of people who
are listening to this haven't yet
subscribed. So if this content has
helped you build smarter, hit that
subscribe button and maybe a like. All
right, back to the episode. Hello and
welcome not just to another episode of
the AI Native Dev, but also to 2026.
Amazing.
>> Insane. You know, it was still hard a
little bit to gro it.
>> I'm Sabin Maple. I'm one of your hosts
of the A Native Dev.
>> And I'm Garney. I am the co-host here
and uh CEO and founder of Tessle.
>> Yeah. Amazing. So this is one of the
episodes that we do uh well I say every
year we've done we're actually only 18
months old so every year it's already a
tradition that we're we're officially
making it a tradition by sort of making
it the second time.
>> It's routine now. So we are going to do
a uh a look back on 2025 um and a look
forward to let's predict some of the
things that are going to happen that we
are almost you know we can easily
predict AI changes and and and paths.
>> It's uh it's like sort of taking candy
for a baby. [laughter]
It's so easy to sort of know what's
going to come in
>> and we'll prove it just by looking back
at some of our 2025 predictions and and
showing how nailed on those predictions
were. Um, a lot happened in 2025.
>> A lot.
>> Do you want some stats about the
podcast?
>> Yeah, I would love it.
>> We had 53 podcast episodes. Um, which is
well, we do one a week, so that's kind
of expected, but it's nice to know that
we're hitting that cadence.
>> U, so some proof of the numbers of it.
That's a lot of content. That's like
many many hours of kind of conversations
and each of those things has a whole
bunch of work ahead of time and then you
know uh uh of course after for editing
and posting.
>> Absolutely. Absolutely. And how many
views do you think so on the AI native
dev YouTube? Of course we have the
podcast. It's mostly podcast. We have a
few other videos but how many views do
you think we had? I know you know. So
maybe maybe let's see your acting skills
here guys. How many views do you think
we had on
>> I think we got 87 views.
>> 87
>> 87. Yeah. I think it's like all of your
friends, right?
>> Slightly lower. Actually, [laughter]
>> we had we had over 1 million views
across the across the year on the AI
native dev YouTube alone uh which is
which is amazing. We have
>> it's insane and I think it's a testament
to just sort of how engaging this domain
is, right? What we try to do here is we
try to um you know kind of capture and
try to distill and debate you know a
bunch of just the action that is going
on and so much is happening in the world
of AI dev you know you it's very hard to
kind of keep up and you know hopefully
we pay a little bit of a service of it
but I think just sort of the amount of
interest the amount of views the amount
of great feedback we get uh is uh is
kind of a good demonstration that you
know this is just a it's a domain where
we all need to kind of work together to
try to sort of uh uh uh maintain a grip
on uh on the changes
>> and we'll try and push out as much great
content as we absolutely can. Uh we have
just over 45,000 subscribers across
across all across all platforms. Um 190
shorts and of course we release these
episodes in a number of different ways.
Some shorts and some some uh cut down
versions where I think they're about 10
minutes or so and we get we get some of
the best bits. Uh our most listened to
episode first of all who do you think
the host was guy? You or me?
>> Ooh. Uh well you're far more
entertaining. Well, I would imagine that
it's you on the
>> but the people didn't go for that guy.
Weirdly, [laughter]
>> your episode with Olivia Pomel, CEO of
CEO of Data Dog.
>> Yeah. All is amazing. You know, it's got
so many sort of deep insights on it and
is so sort of driven, right? Sort of
running the sort of what is it like $40
billion if that's the right number right
now? Like insane company on it. Still so
close to the metal and has such great
insights.
>> Yeah. Over 50,000 views on that post.
Let's go into a few of them. Let's let's
look at some anecdotes and and let's dig
into some of our favorite episodes,
favorite learnings, um interesting
thought process that we had. Uh way back
when I was looking at the the very first
episode we did in 2025. Uh it was Macy
Baker. Macy's uh here at Tesla uh
working across AI engineering and now
the Devril group. Um and she's a
community engineer. Uh it was all around
prompt engineering and that was
something which was I don't know it felt
like such a buzz word back in the day.
Yeah. Now, we don't talk about proper
jobs that much.
>> Yeah. Official official jobs that have
been posted. First of all, I think it
was a really fun episode on it. And I
think I don't know if it was like our
first episode that was uh really kind of
purely playful, right, of just sort of
enjoying a little bit the wonder that is
uh that is LLM, right? We did the sort
of deception games, right? The
>> uh and uh and you know, Macy's is
incredible, you know? So, so that's an
advantage over there. But yeah, it does
feel like in general like you look at
2025 and you look at the beginning of
the year and you think about LLMs and
prompts and uh I mean it really feels
like at least a decade ago, you know, in
uh just sort of normal time just just
sort of mental time of like what were we
thinking a year ago.
>> Mhm. Yeah. And and of course leaning
more into agents now we lean more into
context versus prompts with with pure
LLMs. We had a couple of really
interesting uh sessions that I uh had.
One with Max uh in the AI engineering
team uh giving us a nice 101 with prompt
with agents, but also with Yaniv and
Yian was doing a bunch of work uh
looking at the interactions between an
agent and uh and an LLM. Yeah. more kind
of like man-in-the-middle looking at
looking at the discussions that was
going um between very very interesting
breakdowns on the different tool usage
that uh Claude versus uh OpenAI's um uh
agent and also Gemini CLI of course and
recognizing there are significant
differences between the number of tools
the tool usage and also the system
prompts the style of system prompts that
each have super interesting uh session
essentially contra in those different
approaches.
>> Yeah. And I think that one is like a
recent one so it's easy to relate to the
um kind of the current interest level,
right? I think to an extent when you
look at both the sort of the you know
the Macy episode way back when uh and
kind of the oneonone 101 on agents is
it's interesting there's basically a
whole exercise of reverse engineering
how do these creatures uh behave right
and and it's it's weird like when you
stop to think about sort of AI and
development like suddenly we need to
kind of infer behavior you know like try
to understand the behavior of the tools
that we are using uh which is uh which
is new I mean I think we're getting used
to it but that thread actually continues
all the way from understanding how would
they behave in prompts and how would we
sort of tell them things to how do they
behave now in agents you know mode and
and how do they interact with tools it's
still about how do you how do you guide
these creatures
>> it's so interesting because now we've
essentially got two black boxes right
you've got the black box of the LLM
which is how is it coming to this this
answer how is it providing this response
and you got this black box of the agent
how is it actually going to go go about
trying to get this response what tools
is is it going to use is it how is it
going to use the context what context
should it pull in should it reach out
for when should it do web searches, when
should it read the file system. You've
got these two layers now which are it's
quite hard to navigate
>> and it's different degrees of freedom
and I think it's important to remember
that it's actually always the model
right like even the agents the agents
have no intelligence in them right they
are just facilitators of combinations uh
but I think you know as as in was
pointing out in the in the episode uh
you know it's interesting to think about
how how often are the models tuned to
the agents uh versus uh how much are
they just sort of generic models that
you know the agent is now just an
interface to them right as sort of Boris
says with uh with this building of cloud
code. But I think in in in all of those
cases, it's just the degrees of freedom.
Like as we try to make more, you know,
to do more with these agents or with
this with AI, right, with sort of these
LLMs, um we we sort of just encounter
more of these degrees of freedom, these
variability. And figuring out how to how
to kind of wrangle that uh is is hard.
So before we were trying to find the
kind of the magic incantations, you
know, now we we have more tools in our
disposal, you know, like the literal
tools of like the tools that we give the
agents, but also just sort of means of
managing, you know, context. That's why
it kind of went from prompt to context.
Like prompt is one form of context, you
know, there's so much more.
>> Yeah. And we'll jump into agents a
little bit more. Um, but let's look at
some of the I guess some of the news
that that happened in and around the
topics that we were talking about over
over the
>> over the time. So I think what I love is
like a lot of the conversations uh that
we've had over the year over the year uh
have to do with sort of product scope,
right? Like we're in AI dev. Part of it
is like these sort of models and their
brilliance and their sort of not so
brilliance. You know, how do we how do
we sort of deal with that? Uh but a lot
of it is like you know what what what
does a dev stack look like? You know,
what are the tools? Uh and I feel like
there were a bunch of things that we
kind of foreshadowed a little bit like
we had good conversations with some
thought leaders. this again we're we're
sort of here to sort of bring the smart
folks over uh and uh and they you know a
lot of the conversations and their views
have kind of ended up panning out right
one that really stuck with me is uh the
conversation we had late in the year
with Mariel from uh graphite uh and they
of course you know towards the end of
the year got acquired by cursor and a
lot of my conversation with graphite was
with with Mariel was on uh well like if
the review agent uh you know can
automatically identify issues why
wouldn't the agent earlier on just sort
of find those problems and if you can
sort of modify and fix problems uh at
the review agent right there without
going back isn't that an agent now and
you know should these two products
really be distinct product on it you
know Merryill had good responses at the
time on it couldn't sort of say well you
know what cursor is [laughter] about to
par and I don't know maybe I don't know
if he did or didn't know at the time uh
but it was interesting to see how that
conversation you know clearly kind of
panned out and cursor now acquired
graphite
>> I'm sure the folks at any sphere listen
to the podcast
>> I probably gave them the idea Yeah, what
guy is saying makes sense.
>> Why aren't we doing that? Yeah.
[laughter]
>> Like go let's go. Uh but congrats to
Merit on it. Um we also had you had a
great conversation uh with the Slack AI
lead.
>> Yes. Yeah, absolutely. Uh with Samuel
Messing and uh it's super interesting
because we were talking a little bit
about how agents are being used these
days and of course with the with the
terminal approach of you of developers
interacting with with coding agents. Uh
it's very interesting that actually chat
is becoming a far more interesting uh
means of of communication. We're not
doing this as much if you look at the
terminal UIs in IDEs. Of course there
are there are alternatives like curses
and people like that
>> but when we start almost anchoring
ourselves in this more chatbased system
we have better chat environments than a
terminal.
>> Why not Slack? And so we discussed the
opportunity or the the the the value in
rather than engaging with a with an AI
coding agent in a terminal, why not do
it in a place that already has the best
environment for discussion uh
collaborative discussion as well with
channels etc to happen. Why not Slack?
Uh and we talked about a little bit
about Devon and how this is really where
Devon started and of course they added
their integrations into Slack. Um uh of
course uh Claude Code now has a Slack
integration that was released month a
few months after we talked about it
again. So what's happening?
>> I think I think you can officially say
that this podcast is a mover and shaker
like stage. It's the only reasonable
explanation for why all of these like
moves happen so shortly after uh we
discussed them.
>> I mean the alternative is we're just
stating the obvious guy and I don't want
to even entertain that uh that that
>> No, now you're just stating the obvious.
[laughter] But uh I do think it's really
interesting uh um uh Steve has uh a
mental model to talk about maturity of
uh of development or kind of an
evolution and it was interesting to to
think about that slack conversation in
that context right you go from uh from
kind of a focus on the code and you know
you need to be in an environment like
the IDE in which you are editing the
code to kind of increasing decoration
like you go from uh I liked his view of
like the chat window is uh small and
then it gets it's bigger that's so the
you know your chat pane in your IDE
becomes the primary dominant you just
sort of look at the code and then you go
to terminal and it's interesting to
think about sort of slack as a
continuation of that um so it's
interesting because that really flips
when you think about product scoping on
it that you know further sort of flips
it around uh and so some IDs you see
anti-gravity coming along and such might
be um you know kind of introducing more
chat and like leaning into I'll create a
new interface and others are indeed you
had a chat interface so I thought that
was really really interesting And uh uh
again, you know, a little bit of a a
little bit of foresight here.
>> Yeah.
>> Um and then I guess, you know, where we
did state the obvious a little bit maybe
was with base 44. And so we had more on
the show on it. Uh he already built
something amazing, you know, kind of
built a kind of a vibe coding platform
sort of lovable bold style on it in uh
uh I think in about six months got
acquired for some sort of silly amount
uh by um by uh weeks and it came on. We
had sort of great conversations on it. I
wanted to test out. He was saying that
in uh he thinks in six months uh you'd
be able to build B 44 with B 44. Uh I
didn't have time to sort of test that
out. I feel like it doesn't sound as
far-fetched uh at the moment. Uh but
what we did see is uh in Wix's Q3
earnings uh we see that definitely
hasn't uh slowed down the growth of it.
Right. And just sort of quoting some
numbers here, uh they now have 2 million
users uh served per that announcement,
which is about seven times increase from
the acquisition, I think five or four
months prior. Uh and you know, they
talked about over a thousand paying
subscribers added every day. And they do
have numbers that are they're not quite
the sort of
I don't know how to sort of say like
they are ridiculous numbers. They're not
quite as ridiculous as numbers you see
from from Lovable, right, going to 200
million ARR. But still you know that was
uh uh while it was a quick acquisition
and an expensive one for weeks like
clearly you know it is paying out in
dividends. Congrats to more and
>> absolutely and and when you think base
44 was I think there were like six six
people.
>> No no no just him. Uh there was the
whole notion with sort of base 44 is
basically him. I think about a month
before the acquisition they hired one
person fully bootstrapped and he just
sort of built that with it. And I think
with today's agents, they're also
getting better and better, and you might
start imagining that being plausible.
Yeah. Uh, but we had another episode of
my conversation with Tom Hume around
kind of debunk debunking the the myth of
the sort of billion dollar sort of
single person organization. That's
probably the closest that they got to
that. I stand behind what I in my
conversation with Tom said uh which is I
think you'd be able to have one person
produce value that a few years ago would
have been worth a billion dollars but
because one person can do that many
individuals can do that now.
>> Yeah. uh there's a new baseline I guess
in
>> and I think in you know we'll kind of
get to this a little bit in the
predictions on it but I think one of the
questions is today there's a lot of
value arbitrage by the people that are
sort of the the the fast movers right
and they come along and they create a
lovable like system and now they're
building on the brand and and those
capabilities the capabilities themselves
that they are building no longer feel
quite as differentiated right you can
build a base 44 with base 44 it means
it's easy to create base 44 um and so
it's really a lot more about that sort
of you know time to market and then can
you now conquer it with some form of
network effect and uh and brand and you
know just sort of a sheer scale
economies
>> can you build those out but it's
interesting to sort of see how uh how
these kind of built up and how the fast
movers you know we don't hear about the
ones that failed but yeah the fast
movers uh that succeed uh managed to
sort of rip so much value very quickly
but I still don't think that they're
going to be you know like a single
person billion dollar company because
others will just mimic that.
>> Yeah. Yeah. for our guests as well. It's
been exciting. Uh lots of lots of you
you've created a list here of
>> it's not just it's not just a foresight
that we had on it. It's also it's a it's
good luck. You should come on the
podcast uh because uh good things will
happen to you. You know I just sort of
created a quick list of it. We had Queen
Slack the SourceCraft CEO come along. We
had a lot of great conversations on it.
Uh they've of course launched AMP as a
as a dev agent which you know in a world
in which it's very hard to stand out on
it. they really managed to sort of
innovate and build a bunch of things
that are unique. Uh and they've since
split off the company and Quinn is now
the CEO of AMP and uh has uh uh uh
another team member running source
itself. So definitely leaned into it. Uh
Mati from 11 Labs was here. Uh that was
a really fun conversation. Love Mati.
Love what they're building. Uh
interesting. So they've raised twice
since that since that round. I think the
last one was sort of $6 billion or maybe
a little bit over. Uh funny thing is uh
you know in the conversation and
actually in many conversations I've had
with Mati uh I talked uh they had this
sort of uh clarity around they're an
audio AI company uh in their last
announcements they now do some video and
all that again product scoping it's all
blending also a bit of a fan anecdote we
talked a lot about their no titles uh uh
message that at the time felt
controversial we've since embraced that
here at Tesl having kind of no titles
>> yeah now now we're just guy and the
minions [laughter]
don't say that offici Oh, sorry. We
don't say that officially.
>> Oh, yeah. That was the private doc.
That's the That's the DM that you sent
me. That's right. That's right.
>> I'm no value to confidentiality
[laughter] here. Um, but no, we had
other great ones. We had Victor from
Synthesia. They they've been rumored to
raise around at $4 billion. We had
Matteo from Lera building AI security
solution that got acquired by
Checkpoint. Uh, of course, Merryill from
Graphite that we mentioned. So yeah, all
in all, I think if you're a startup
founder, you're building something
exciting on it, you manage to get on the
podcast on it, your odds of being
acquired or sort of raising on the round
of are clearly statistically
significant.
>> Yeah, we should we should uh we should
add that as a tagline. Yeah,
>> charge charge a fee of it. You can come
in, we're going to get 2% carry.
Well, I mean, it's testament to like
some of the amazing guests that we've
had on the uh on
>> and that's been very humbling and I I
think uh you know, we don't uh clearly a
lot of this is sort of the back channel
of it, but uh I think you know, first of
all, we're very thankful to all the all
of you listeners, right? you sort of
come along, you ask uh uh you ask us for
sort of topics on it and we uh we try to
debate those and we love the
interactions post but also as our
audience grows you know we've had a lot
of really great inbounds and sort of you
know very smart and capable people
wanting to come on wanting to share
their views and that of course creates a
bit of a flywheel for uh for the podcast
itself. So basically the more you listen
the more you advocate uh and sort of
spread the podcast the better the guests
that we can bring you uh and kind of
have have them sort of share their
views.
>> Absolutely. We're always open to
suggestions as well. So, do please if
there's someone you feel would be, you
know, you'd love for us to chat to and
interview and talk through their their
thoughts, uh, let us know. Uh, podcast
at tesla.io. Um, and and we'll we'll
we'll work through that. Um, so let's
talk a little bit about some of the some
of the things that that we observed in
the market, I guess, on the AI
>> kind of thing happening in the market in
2025. Bit
>> news a year.
>> There were a couple of minor things. I
saw one thing on the register that
happened that we should maybe talk. But
but no, I think the big thing that kind
of the big shaker and I guess we we we
noticed this at Tesla obviously when we
when we were you know adjusting to to to
market changes
>> was was agents and how much agents
really grabbed hold of of the interest
of every company that is thinking about
AI using AI building with AI and and
obviously it you know it also made a
change in the way we at Tesla think
about our products think about our
positioning in the market
>> um so so in terms of the market Let's
let's start with the market.
>> Yeah, I think agents are clearly the
biggest like ami amidst to the you know
many things that happened this year. Uh
this was I guess as predicted a little
bit at the beginning of the year the
year of the agent. Uh and specifically
in the world of development uh I think
the the uh advent of cloud code u and
sort of sonnet 37 and you know the
strength
>> at least at the same time.
>> Yeah. Well I think cloud code was was
around for a bit before but it really
kind of started shining you know when
sonnet 37 came out. uh and its kind of
capabilities around coding. And so I'd
say in that sort of April May time frame
uh there was a bit uh sort of really a a
corner uh kind of turned uh and and and
significant progress made in just how
usable development agents uh are. I mean
they existed before. Agentic frameworks
existed. Uh Devon existed. Um you know
there were there were a variety of
agents but I think it just made it
practical and you can really see the
turning point uh in terms of adoption in
terms of usage uh and
in terms of the ability of of the likes
of us you know at Tessle and many
companies to now bet on agents. Yeah. Uh
and so there was a very to me a very
clear delineation of the before and
after. There was a lot of progress going
leading up to that sort of Aprilish time
frame, but I think from a development
perspective, the world has basically
become agentic
>> roughly in that sort of uh April May
time frame.
>> And of course, 37 was was probably one
of the first more public more well-known
reasoning models or or models that
provided a reasoning capability. Do do
you feel like that played a part in
success of agents or do you think that
would have just kind of you know
>> I think it's a it's a combination of
many things. I mean I think you know
OpenAI clearly sort of introduced
reasoning right with their sort of 01 uh
model of it. I think I think Son of 37
was the first one that had the the the
broader like the gradual sort of
thinking how how much is your thinking
budget. I think it played a role but
more than that is I I think uh Anthropic
just managed to to build a model that
was better on the coding front and then
to to build this interface with cloud
code to really interact with it. And so
you know one element was just the sheer
success of it and they've been using
cloud code internally before and so they
knew that it was successful and you know
Boris uh the creator of cloud code talks
a lot about how you know for him it was
just almost by by accident that I
started writing code. It was just about
creating an interface to the model. Um
but a lot of the um and you know a lot
of the details of those you know evolved
over time but creating that interface in
which you are not focusing on the code
you are in terminal and so the code is
secondary and then having the agentic
search I think that level up you know
being able to use the local tools in the
terminal uh and be able to search. I
think both of those alongside that sort
of core model have uh have combined uh
for something great. I don't know. I I
think it's hard to really pinpoint one
thing, but what I think you can say very
clearly is that the interface of cloud
code uh has kind of tapped into a bunch
of those strengths in a very kind of
powerful way
>> that just just made it more likely to
succeed, made it sort of feel the magic.
Uh and the UX I guess I guess as the
year's gone on the more and more that
that their team has added to those types
of things whether it's whether it's
hooks whether it's claude skills is a
great example whether it's uh the
integrations like very interesting
browser integrations that were kind of
released at the end of last year as
well.
>> Yeah and around that I think uh the the
two other sort of interesting phenomenas
that you can say about agents this year
is uh the adoption of MCP and agent
skills as standards. Um I think what's
interesting so MCP technically launched
uh the year before you mentioned uh 2024
um but uh it was really very widely
adopted including by anthropic
competitors throughout 2025 and fairly
early in 2025 and that was interesting.
It was sort of a bit of a a non-obvious
move you know by the ecosystem to to
embrace the protocol. The protocol
remains like amazing and horrible at the
same time. is a very immature uh uh
protocol in in various ways but it's
also you know a really great boost to
create standardized way of connecting
any software any capabilities into the
world and then as that evolved and
people abused MCPS and there were sort
of not enough and our knowledge of agent
grew and uh claude or anthropic launched
claude skills and then created an an
open standard version of that as agent
skills and it looks like sort of jer is
still a bit out but it looks like agent
skills are, you know, they're definitely
initially supported by many other comp
competitive agents. Uh, and so that's
interesting. First of all, like kudos to
Anthropic for releasing things that are
useful enough
>> uh that uh that really even the
competitors understand that it is useful
to kind of boost the ecosystem with
them. Uh, and so that's been great and
seeing them do it again.
>> I'm wanting to see the advancements
through the standards as well, which is
which is wonderful because not not
everyone does that. I you know most
would probably go well actually let's
create my proprietary claude skills and
lead it there let's not worry about what
others are doing but this is this is a a
big useful step for the market not just
>> I I I agree and I think uh it's
interesting to sort of see them be the
trends setter and in general as you
track agents over time I think what you
could see is you know in most cases
cloud code was was the leader in kind of
setting the trend of how products would
work like ms became you know were
initially introduced into cloud code and
then they became prevalent elsewhere.
You know, commands I think are initially
cloud code and became fairly prevalent.
Uh I do want to give a shout out to the
cursor team though because cursor rules
have existed for a very long time and in
many ways skills are very much like uh
they're a bit more kind of uh native to
the model, you know, so they're like a
little bit uh um they're different in a
variety of ways. uh but I do think that
the the idea of sort of structured
instructions or sort of reusable context
uh is uh is very much there. So it's
been great to sort of see see the
leadership see the collaboration and of
course kind of culminated late in the
year by the creating of a Linux
foundation uh um uh sort of sub
foundation dedicated to uh to AI open
infrastructure. Um I'm very curious to
see how uh a Linux foundation uh or in
generally kind of an open source
foundation can deal with the pace of
change uh on it. It's uh there's a lot
that I love about you know foundations
and uh and uh open source uh pace is not
historically been the some of the uh
strongest suit uh but I love the kind of
contribution of I think skills have been
donated uh uh agents MD has been uh
donated over there the uh goose uh agent
is there so it'll be interesting to sort
of see I I I hope to see a lot of great
things in 2026 around the open agent
ecosystem we already had open weight
models. I think we increasingly have
substantial open source software and how
do those interact with the commercial
players who are raising you know
ridiculous amounts at ridiculous
valuations and so they do need to build
a a strong business around them
>> collectively uh competitors to to to uh
to claude code. We should also say yeah
codeex making big strides as well. uh
Gemini CLI. I hear a ton of people uh
saying how much how much the competitors
have got closer and and have improved
and people really you know many
preferring those different those
different agents as well. So going to be
an interesting year and we can maybe
talk predictions in a bit but
interesting year to see to see how uh
agents uh compete for for for market
share. Yeah, absolutely. I think we've
seen like a lot of progress over there.
And I do want to point out that also
some independent agents kind of came
along, right? You have Kilo code, you
had goose, you had uh uh uh open hands,
I think, has sort of uh dropped a bit
off the sort of the the chart or maybe
it's just, you know, blended with those
others. Uh but you see a lot of uh open
agents that come along. Kilo code is the
one that really caught my attention just
because sort of built very much to be a
a kind of cross model agent and it was
it's a newer one, so it feels very
modern on it. And I I think the um uh in
many of these different tools, each of
them learned from one another. And so
while Claude set the stage, they're not
the only ones that innovated. You know,
I think Codex, one thing for instance
you can demonstrate is that they
launched initially in the cloud and then
went to the CLI and of course Claude now
has cla
uh versions of it. So people explore
different domains and different paths. I
do think that it's sort of a
non-controversial statement to say that
uh Anthropic has focused a lot more on
sort of the enterprise and uh and are
probably the dominant player when it
comes to development but in the latest
uh iterations and we'll talk about that
in predictions uh the the sheer
capability of the models in development
you know you definitely had there
there's a lot to sort of say for the
Gemini models and worries that they do
better and definitely the gap on OpenAI
and other fronts is smaller Yeah. More
and more as the year went on, um, when
models and things like that got dropped,
did they do you feel like that made as
big a splash as it did a year ago when a
model improvement caused such a big
difference with agents now? Are we do we
care more about other things that
improve the experience? Whether that's
tools, whether that's the awareness of
the project, the context, and things
like that. Do we care more about that
versus the intelligence of the
underlying model?
>> It's a good question. I mean, I think
again, one year feels like a lifetime.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. And so if you hearken
back uh earlier in the year there was a
lot of conversation about uh the rumored
failed training runs of um at the time I
think it was Llama 4 and you know
whatever the sort of the next big models
uh of the versions and uh the the
growing kind of perspective uh in the
world of sort of AI research has become
that the value is no longer in
pre-training it is in post-training. and
a lot of the uh the refinements that
come after and then later on of course
in Agentic. Um I do think that uh Google
kind of rocked that boat a little bit
with their latest models, right? I think
it was in November that they launched uh
uh released a a whole slew of models
that were substantially better and
OpenAI announced the sort of code red
right about the reach of them. You also
see a lot of the dynamics of existing
distribution uh play out. You see Meta
AI with their reach. You see Google with
their reach. You see Grock and Twitter
with their reach. And so uh I I think um
the the the world of research has kind
of moved into more post-training and
refinement uh than the um uh than the
pre-training but maybe that you know got
a little bit is a bit challenged by uh
um uh by the Google releases. And if you
if you listen to uh Eli Saskover in the
latest episode he had with Dwarkkesh uh
he talks about you know the this is
going to be the year of re the year of
research. uh and coming back to sort of
thinking about different so I I'd say
this year probably true that model
improvements maybe in the second half of
the year were not as dominant um uh I
think OpenAI had a bad year in that
sense it had a lot of incremental
improvements but they didn't have a big
splash moment of this model maybe Sora
is the example uh like the counter
example but in the dev world I think uh
I think uh Anthropic and and Google kind
of got more of the headlines
um while OpenAI kind of kept up but they
sort of didn't lead uh those charts as
much. Um but I I wouldn't rule it out in
the uh in the long term like I think
there's still uh that's one thing that
is hard for me to predict. Research is
very like uh hit and miss.
>> Of course on the flip side context and
those types of things have made
[clears throat] a massive improvement in
terms of the way we use agents.
>> And I think so I think that to me is is
a very very big takeaway. It's close to
heart kind of here at Tesla.
uh I think this what has very much
happened post agents maybe in the last
sort of four or five months is the
acceptance that knowledge and
intelligence are not the same and so all
these models are becoming very
intelligent. The agents make them you
know they they capitalize on that to to
give them arms and legs right to allow
them to go off and and invoke tools and
gather more information and gather
knowledge. uh but what we also see is
that to be a great and powerful
developer you know that is using you
know that's truly AI native and you know
is is whatever 100x productive a lot of
it comes down to context a lot of it
comes down to you wrote the right
instructions the right summaries you
kept the docs in a certain place uh you
you can pull down the right information
at the right time and do context
management so you don't sort of overflow
uh the uh the agent when you give it
information you name things correct
directly so the agent can find them
where relevant uh and and you so you see
this in the practices uh you see it in
the platforms themselves and so Gemini
has their sort of CLI extensions but
more notably cloud launched skills
GitHub has copilot spaces uh you know
just of course cursor has always had
rules and they launched team rules on it
so a lot of investments in the platform
in really reusable context right it says
maybe the agent is very intelligent uh
and it is becoming more and more
intelligent. But when you want it to uh
you know use a certain library, you
don't want it to need to analyze the
code of the library. It's better if it
has docs that teach it. If you want it
to um uh code the way you want to
develop in a certain organization, it
needs to know what the best practices
are. You know, it it it shouldn't just
need to kind of infer them dynamically
from historical code. And and so this
idea that if uh if you hearken back to
my conversation with um uh with guy uh
Guri from augment you know a lot of
their core competency was around
learning from the codebase and I think
their initial premise I hope I'm not
sort of misrepresenting his view here
was that they will they will train on
the codebase and they will kind of
understand the codebase for them they
built it into this rag like you'll kind
of real time augment it but it was all
within that intelligence like it will be
fed fetched dynamically and
intelligently and magically in Elby the
system you had poolside last year they
were more training on the codebase and
uh and I think today there's more
acceptancees that it'll be more like a
support knowledge base it's more learn
from these systems extract out of them
your instructions and then keep those
and then monitor and manage those and I
think that is that is uh very aligned
with with kind of our view of the world
at Tesl We talk about sort of
specentcentric software which is
increasingly what you know what you what
you want is to capture intent capture
knowledge and then provide that in a
smart way which is not easy to the agent
and then have the agent uh uh build on
it. So so that was uh uh to me a
positive and maturing sort of step
forward uh in getting agents and uh and
LLMs to to help us build offer.
>> Yeah. And I think a lot of the from a
usage point of view, a lot of
frustrations from a developer using
agents will very much occur when whether
it's anything as simple as a style, a
way that a developer wants to write code
all the way through to whether it's
organizational policies or like you say
the way this code has been written in my
codebase today. The an LLM can very
often provide a a correct answer back to
a user. But if it's not the correct
answer that a user wants to wants to see
in in a way that they want to see it, it
creates frustrations and actually the
the value of that agent uh becomes far
less because yes, it provides me the
right response, but now I have to go in
and and and update it and and make
changes uh to to the answer to make it
to make it, you know, to allow me to
actually be able to check it in as is.
Yeah. Um and that frustration I think
with that with the with the context with
that ability to look as to not just how
something could be done but how
something should be done really unlocks
the the way in which a developer can
actually reduce that frustration and get
what they actually want to see right
>> and and reduce that time.
>> Yeah, I agree with that and I I'll
further emphasize that the fact that you
need to review in the first place
>> uh is a big limiting factor in how
productive you can be. So the more you
can say upfront and trust that it will
be applied the the more you can delegate
uh and the more successful you can do
that.
>> Yeah. And I think what we what we see so
so we see this context manifest in many
ways uh through the system uh and maybe
it's worth kind of relating it to tessle
and so so tesl uh just as a quick
journey right we sort of said hey spec
centric software will be the future and
you know over time you know you the
importance of the code will diminish
that's what we've been saying all along
uh in favor of kind of captured intent
and I think that's happening I think the
world is moving towards that destination
I think what we see is there are maybe
like two versions of that that uh that
manifested. One is uh the the advent of
specd driven development. Uh and so
that's more about uh when the agent
approaches a task,
>> not have it like be before it writes the
code stop and create a plan. Uh and so
that uh that has now fairly quickly as
these things happen in this world has
just sort of become a core part of the
way the agents build. You know, you see
Claude often times defaulting to plan
mode uh and starting by creating a plan.
You see uh anti-gravity which is sort of
the the windsurf kind of rebranding or
like created on the on the backs if
shall we say of sort of windsurf post
the Google acquisition. You see that you
know creating plans and implementations
plan ahead of time and then you see
external frameworks like speckit from uh
uh from github and you see of course
kirao and you know that we've had here.
So you see all of those creating specd
driven development that's sort of that's
more about um uh uh the mode of
interaction with the agent being hey
let's form a plan together. Yeah.
>> Uh take everything you understand you
know here's what I want. Take everything
you understood about what I told you and
what I what I what I want to achieve.
Take everything you understand about my
current reality and then put together a
plan and let us review it and then
execute to the plan and and you know
draw within the lines right like stay
stay roughly there. And so I think that
has gone from are you kidding me this is
overhead I don't want to slow down to
yeah of course this is the way that you
build in in the span of three months you
know something like that um and we very
much sort of felt that with the Tessle
framework uh that we released which you
know a lot of its goal was to say hey
agent hold off you know wait write the
spec create them uh and uh and and and
only then kind of go off and update
>> and to remind people the the Tesla
framework that you're referring to
there. Uh this was the this is not the
spec registry that we that we're you
know very very much focused on today.
This is more the specentric way of
building software. So this is writing
the spec that you then generate that
code from using using.
>> Exactly. And that ended up being kind of
the SD but and so we we had a lot of
learning on that and I think in in in
many ways this has precisely happened
but it turned out that it really needs
to be sort of embedded into the agent.
And then the the second version of
context that came along is uh is more
the sort of the long lived uh specs that
talk about how you want to build. What
is my environment like? What is the sort
of the the correct way for the agent to
sort of produce software? What does good
software look like in my environment?
Including sometimes product
functionality of like how do things
work? Whether it's how to use them or to
be able to leave a trail behind you,
right, of uh of uh of what is the
functionality that is left. And so all
of those are now fall not under SDDD but
rather under context engineering or sort
of context management
>> which is a massive term that's been
repeated again and again and again by
the whole market the importance of
context management and context
engineering.
>> Absolutely. And so and over there so
context management has its own kind of
layer of it for Tesla right now that's a
lot of our focus on to say well how do
you how do you create the right context
in the first place so you know how do
you not require the agent to uh either
have it all the info kind of
internalized in its brain uh ahead of
time you know which is clearly not
relevant when things are dynamic but
also not need to go and like read up
massive code bases and get them
correctly and not make mistakes and uh
you know read documents But practice
like you have to create those documents
be intentional about what it is that you
want. Uh we have a lot of data. We've
discussed some of that with these
evaluations for instance in the Aniv uh
in the episode with YNive uh talking
about how how to evaluate those. So how
do you create evaluation scenarios and
we should probably go back a little bit
to the uh the benchmarking
>> uh but how do you how do you evaluate
like you say words on it and you know
like I tell you words all the time and
you never listen. Uh so you know like
sometimes [laughter]
So, so you know agents are sometimes the
same. So, how do we how do we kind of
evaluate and how how do you know whether
the agents work? How do you know if the
new fancy expensive model uh will will
be worth your dollars versus you know
how uh how do you know if like the sort
of cheaper open model or optimized model
maybe that does the job and it's a lot
cheaper a lot faster. So, how do you
generate that context? How do you
evaluate it to know it? How do you
distribute it? Like there's so much to
say.
>> Yeah. uh how do you get it to the agents
and of course how do you get them to
load the right context at the right time
and then how do you kind of observe
things over time. So all of that world
of context engineering that you know
we've we've grown to think of as not
just context engineering but rather
agent enablement you know like how do
you how do you kind of enable the agent
with the right information at the right
time and then how do you how do you kind
of own this knowledge this layer of
intent this layer of of of of knowledge
you know uh of context uh how do you
manage that over time keep it keep it up
to date change it as models change and
so I think this is a brave new world of
of context that is very very aligned
with with our kind of original vision at
Tessle of it will become specentric swap
the word spec for you know spec and
knowledge and context and you know these
are all like synonyms really um and uh
and how do you how do you develop in
that world
>> and very interesting that that you know
the way the way we used to talk about
prompts I say I say a year ago like like
we're talking a decade ago but it feels
like that when we talk about prompts
where we where we talk about you know
using the correct language and people
thinking about prompt engineers where
you need to craft a prompt in a specific
way and then not just holding that to
one developer or first of all
understanding what is the right thing.
The evaluations are super important for
that when we when we l think more on the
context side. Um but then secondly that
distribution that when a developer gets
that prompt correct um there was the
thought of okay can we and I know some
tools did this as well. um can we share
these prompts across so that if I want
to correct if I wanted to create a bunch
of test cases or if I wanted to do some
code reviews I'm using the correct
prompt to guide the the LLM uh in the
right way. Now in context, we're hearing
all those echoes in the same way. Okay,
I create context. How do I know that
context is wellformed is correctly
written so that an agent can best
consume it? Evals, the ability to
actually eval that context to say yes,
this is good context. No, this context
isn't written well. You need to
structure it in a in a different way to
to get the most out of it from an agent.
And then of course that distribution
that when we get that context right okay
if it's a policy thing well it's not
just me that has to adhere to that
policy in an organized particularly an
enterprise uh organization and
enterprises in particular they have huge
numbers of developers huge teams that
that needs to be distributed to you
can't just have one developer or a small
subset of developers contributing some
code which is either against policy or
against the way most the rest of the
organization wants to build. So all of
these challenges just magnify as soon as
we think about it in the larger
organization and the the the team
development
>> and I think a lot of it uh first of all
like I love the analogy to the LLM and
you know we've again we sort of felt it
over here right like we built a whole
might I say sort of impressive
evaluation system for prompts and a lot
of that needed to be sort of thrown by
the wayside you know in favor of an
evaluation system that is agent-based
because that's the sort of the right way
to interact a lot of the sort of you
know reverse engineering of like how
does it work how do you affect it I
think what has changed is this is the
scope of the task you know and uh and in
the in the prompt you you expect at a
level you know of of of accomplishment
in the reasoning maybe a little bit more
and then of course you know you get to
uh to the agents of today so I think we
definitely need to build that but I
think a lot of the analogy here is that
as the task grows it becomes like a
larger organization you know and when
you have a lot of people you know they
can all be you hired amazing people
they're very intelligent but in addition
to to kind of like as the scope of the
task grows it becomes a lot more like
managing organizations, right? And you
know, you have a whole pile of people,
right? You have a group of intelligent
people, right? You know, building out uh
and they still needs to be aligned like
it's still hard to say, okay, we sat
down and we discussed the thing and we
agreed that we will do it. Do we
remember? Do we know to go and read the
right document at the right time, you
know, to uh to perform an action? to
remember like our own sort of selves
from like a year ago, you know, like the
decision that we made so we can kind of
keep to it. And so a lot of these
analogies uh apply now to agents of like
what what do you want to tell them? A
bit of a garbage in garbage out, right?
Like if you gave them the wrong
instructions, if you gave them
irrelevant context, that takes away
tokens, right? They takes away
attention. Uh and so how do you sort of
shrink it? You know, how can you be an
efficient communicator? So a lot of
those human analogies now uh occur and
some organizational philosophy comes
into how do you make agents effective.
>> Yeah. So from the Tesla point of view
and obviously you know context is is a
big part of of what we're building today
and the platform that we're that we're
that we're building. Um one of the terms
that I know and heard every single day
pretty much is agent enablement. And
this is this is super important super
powerful. Talk us through first of all
what is agent enablement and and what's
Tesla's role in that? Yeah, I I feel uh
we we should start discussing in sort of
outcome based tools versus sort of the
technical element. So context is a uh is
a very important uh tool or sort of
means context management of it. I think
the eventual goal that you want is to
enable the agents. Uh and I I find sales
enablement actually to be an easier
example. Uh even though in development
clearly like you think about sort of on
boarding. So for developers you can
think about you need to on board a
developer. Uh so you have a you know a
brilliant developer come along join the
team you still don't expect them to kind
of know how to build well within your
organization the very first moment they
landed you need them to be on boarded so
what are the materials they need to read
and then over time there's some element
of continuous training I think in
development it's a little bit harder to
to to uh uh think about systemizing it
because we rely a lot of individual kind
of skills and individual talents and you
know for good or bad we sort of rely on
this institutional knowledge uh sales
enablement is an interesting analogy
because uh often times as organizations
grow you you want your sales
organization to be creative only to a
degree. You want them to repeat the
playbook and so sales is a much more
structured place in which you say okay
here are the enablement materials. Hey,
any new salesperson, you need to read
this. But also, every existing
salesperson every year at kickoff, we're
going to teach you this is this is the
sales process. These are the stages.
These are the decks that you need to do.
These are the materials, the emphasis,
the messaging, you know, like all the
things that you need to provide. And
then those get measured, you know, and
they get monitored. And we identify the
cases where some random behavior was
successful or when something fells
through. And then you redefine a bunch
of those practices and then you train
them again, you know, to build those.
And so agents are I think that's maybe a
slightly closer technical analogy to
what we do with the agent enablement. So
your eventual goal is to say hey I want
agents to work in my organizations and
specifically in my development uh and in
my codebase. I want them to build well
for me. So how do I how do I make them
successful? What is the knowledge I need
to equip them with? How do I uh uh kind
of evaluate you know role play and test
and sort of see that that works which is
something we can't do as as well with
people. we can be a lot more demanding
with agents. You know, how do I
distribute that knowledge? How do I then
observe behavior and sort of see when
did it actually happen? And then how do
you take that and optimize it? And when
we apply it to agents, we see all these
super interesting things that we'll
continue to share uh over the over the
next uh uh kind of couple of months uh
is all these like really interesting
observations. You know like when when we
when we look at agent logs and what they
create you can see how some instructions
you put in your context u they just
ignore they just don't do and you see
how other instructions they will do it
when we do the the AB test when we
evaluate with and without those
instructions they do the same thing
anyway. So if you try to get it to use
uh git, it would use git anyway, but if
you try to get it to use gh, you know,
instead as the CLI, you you really need
to say it in a very specific way to kind
of counter the intuitive way. And so if
you said git, you wasted context. If you
said gh in the wrong way, you're not
going to get your results. So a lot of a
lot of those and eventually like you
have to think about how do I solve it?
I've observed a problem. And that comes
back to you modify the context. That's
your tool. So we we think a lot about if
you are an organization you want agents
to work for you you need to enable those
agents and context and the management of
that context the optimization of that
context is the means through which you
do it.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. And then I want to say maybe one
thing like the other term that I harp on
a little bit recently is uh agent
experience. Uh, and I think from a from
a from an organization perspective, what
you're doing is your agent enablement,
you know, in your organization instead
of maybe a better term, but when you're
uh say you're an open source maintainer,
right? And you have your library, you
want agents to be able to successfully
use it and you you you build a uh you
know some some some library or some
framework on it. You want developers to
use it and so you invest in developer
experience. You care about your command
line hygiene. You care about sort of
ease of installation. You care about,
you know, sort of self-healing, whether
it's a problem. You care about all these
uh traits, right? Composability, all
these great developer experience traits.
Like, why do you care? It's because you
want people to use the stuff you've
built, right? They're amazing. You want
them to be accessible. You want them to
be used correctly so they don't come
bother you with sort of uh, you know,
silly mistakes. So, with agents, you you
you have the same need. You want agents
to use your software. You want them to
use your tools, you know, you want them
to use them correctly. And context is
often times the means that you have it.
it is both your sort of UX and your your
docs you know at the same time. uh and
so you the kind of the other lens of
enabling agent is a bit more sort of uh
focused on for my piece of software for
my API whether I'm an organization or uh
or uh or sort of an open source
maintainer whatever it is you know for
my open source library uh or a closed
source library I want to provide a great
agent experience which is basically a
form of I want to enable agents
>> mh
>> to be able to consume my my uh my work.
So all of that combines
>> in my granted you know like I'm sort of
deep in this sort of a Kool-Aid uh view
uh into the sort of new reality uh of uh
of software development that is
specentric or like intent centric right
versus um uh versus codecentric in which
what you're capturing what you are
communicating is uh is is how to do
things it's what to do and it's not the
sort of the implementation in the code.
>> It's going to be a big year for context.
It's going to be a big year for
enablement and a big year for Tesla.
Let's that kicks off our predictions
section.
>> Indeed. Tesla will be super fun to build
and super fun to use and hopefully a
massive success.
>> Amazing. Amazing.
>> Okay. So, to to to wrap up this episode,
we're going to finish with not just the
predictions of 2026, but let's see how
favorable or how how how well our
predictions of 2020 how poorly they aged
in 2025. So we'll look at we had kind of
three categories and we'll jump through
these quickly. Uh the first category was
actually my prediction which is we'll
look through we'll look beyond day one
development in 2025 whereby in 2020 uh
2024 we were very very much you know
focused on code generation and building
like throwing out spitting out code left
right and center. I predicted okay we're
going to actually think much much more
about the path beyond day zero beyond
day one and and and so forth. Can we
look more into the testing? Can we look
more into the maintenance and stuff like
that?
>> Did that happen?
>> Not so much. Not so much. Not so much.
Well, I think like two things happen,
right? Like I think I I'd sort of give
you like partial marks on that, you
know, because I feel um uh most of what
grew was more about what we can do with
the agent. So like can I do initial
things bigger? I do think that there's
this advent of an AI native developer
that works in these sort of you know
contextrich way uh and focuses on
delegation and doesn't work and for them
they do think a bit about uh about the
longevity because they would store
artifacts so I think they get some of
those points but I think it hasn't
reached teams like I think it's still in
like
>> single player and it hasn't reached
quality per se it's like purely
functionality
>> yeah I would I would agree with that and
I think you know there's there's a lot
of work that's done in in in the I guess
the reviewing of code that's being
generated, but it's still it's still
very much day zero. It's still in the
pull request of the of the of the piece
of code that's being delivered rather
than the kind of like day one this
already exists. How do we maintain
>> 100%. Yeah.
>> Uh the second the second category was I
guess we were looking at models back
then. So we were looking at model
leaders. Would there be a model lead a
sole model leader or would it still be a
group uh of people kind of like you know
jumping jumping past each other for for
a brief period? Yeah, I think I said at
the time that I that I don't think
there's going to be a leader. And we
talked a lot about fragmentation. It's
like, hey, would organization kind of
pick an a model at the time, you know,
and sort of stick to it. Would they, you
know, would one of them sort of break
out? And says like, there's no way
they're going to come uh and kind of
pass one another. There will be more of
that continuation that we've sort of
seen in 2024. And I think that I think
that happened.
>> I'd say I'd say has I think I think
people are maybe picking between models,
which is another thing that we kind of
like predicted in terms of what's their
need. do they need more of a reasoning
model for this type of task or whatever?
And so, but but yeah, in terms of the
vendors,
yeah, people are people are people are
jumping between and people are depending
on which month you're at, you'll see a
different a different vendor at the top.
And I think they're yeah, keeping up
with each other, which is a good thing.
It's a great thing for the
>> I think a lot of the sort of the the
kind of the um kind of beating one
another is happening of it. I mean, I
sort of give, you know, a few concrete
examples of it. uh Gemini clearly you
know when it came out with with its sort
of latest models in uh in I think
November you know that definitely you
know showcase suddenly is at the top of
all the different benchmarks on it. Uh I
think the other interesting play was uh
cursor launching its own models in
composer which are sort of faster. I
think generally perceived as not um not
uh maybe quite sort of as good at some
things but for specifically others they
might be you know very good and and fast
uh and maybe faster than the others. So
I think that played out uh and I so so I
think there's been a lot of uh there's
still been like you know edging one
another and I think also the the gaps
have shrunk. There has been a lot of uh
there's like almost like a taste element
you know people start developing you
know like I kind of like this model you
know I like their style
>> befriending befriending
>> befriending the model um but I but I
think I think loyalty remains low
>> uh and most organizations remain kind of
multi-tool multimodel uh and generally
when you talk to them we talk to a lot
of enterprises they don't see that
changing
>> yeah yeah I agree uh the third part
obvious part a gem in this one uh when
we're talking about adoption of AI uh in
in in 2025 as you know around tools but
as well as enterprise adoption cursor
grew uh other high adopter tools
continuing to build uh in in popularity
generally yeah we saw that enterprise
adoption more being on AI growth and and
AI enterprises continuing to invest
absolutely we see that and actually at a
number of conferences this year I'm I'm
amazed at how many enterprises are
really betting on AI and it's not like
you normal technologies you see the
startups and the smaller companies
betting big and then and then of course
the the enterprises are slow to slow to
come in we're not we're not seeing that
the the the adoption is is
>> there was a strong hiccup you know where
where there were that study that came
out so said that most projects of AI
fail in enterprises and there was like a
a moment of concern that you know would
everybody kind of pull back right and uh
there's definitely still the financial
market concerns about the AI bubble um
but all in all I'd A you know I I guess
at the time we sort of made like two
somewhat obvious predictions on it. So
>> but the gem the gem is the more
crowdsource benchmarks by mid 2025 and
that was that was very close to to to
what actually happened of course with
tweb bench still being obviously very
very much used but tbench coming around
and a number of uh other evaluations. I
know spring uh had their own evaluation
for for um benchmark for for spring
applications and of course basel came
out with their own benchmarks as well
for for nex.js. JS applications. This is
something which people are realizing
there is a need for and and it is being
crowdsourced. So that was a very strong
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I I agree. You know
hopefully you know one a little bit less
obvious but it comes back to almost you
know we have to have a measuring stick.
You know we have to be able to deal with
them and as we do more and more we need
more and more benchmarks. So there's
probably like this year you know we sort
of mentioned a handful over here but I
think the idea of releasing a benchmark
became like a very fashionable thing
right like so many benchmarks around. Uh
and I think that's great. So much so
that there's need for tooling like
tbench right like tooling to create
benchmarks. I mean we're big fans of
tbench you know harbor that we use on
top of that uh as is there sort of the
newer version of it. So you know eval
are kind of growing and I think uh I saw
one post for someone talking about how
developers will become data scientists
which I don't love that analogy but I
think uh there's a grain of truth in
there uh which is you know you have to
embrace this in this world your work
you're producing software through
instructions of the agent and in that
world you you don't have determinism you
know you cannot say you know this works
and this doesn't work you know and what
you need is is statistics
and eval give you that means and so uh I
will I'll sort of say that should that
will continue
>> and the competency of running an eval
defining an eval executing an eval will
be one that will grow both in individual
developers and in development
organizations you know they will need to
have their own benchmarks for what
>> what you know whether an agent is is is
worthy capable uh of performing you know
actions in their in their environment in
their development
>> and of course one of the reasons why
we're building eval as a first class
citizen into into the the the context
management platform that we're building.
>> I think every eventually every
development organization needs to have
benchmarks to say can this agent work in
my environment.
>> Yep. Yep.
>> And of course when there are changes or
when you want to you know compare
whether it's agents or context you have
the ability and the means to do so.
>> Indeed. So let's look forward to 2026
given given given how
>> continue our sort of fool's errand over
here uh yeah [laughter] I think we
weren't like overly audacious in sort of
our uh in our predictions in 2025
>> I think so should we should we see if
there are any audacious
>> we'll see we'll see we're pretty
reasonable
>> people so so I think yeah from from my
point of view I'm I'm going to stay away
from the day one development that's a
manana problem I think so let's talk
about agent usage how people are using
agents um in in 2025 of course
everyone's jumping on the agent train
and it's a case of can we can we pull
this into our organizations can we get
adoption and people are very very much
trying to work out what can we do with
agents how can we pull agents in I think
in 2026 we're going to go to that next
level which is okay we want to be using
agents we're we're trying to adopt
agents we're trying to bring it in
that's a given how do we actually make
sure we are effective at using agents
how do we actually tune the way we're
using agent and I think a lot of this is
going to be you know the means to which
you can provide an agent things like
context but it's also the way in which
we learn to use agents and there are
ways in which we can improve that maybe
maybe it's through uh the means in which
we parallelize agents maybe we break
down tasks and have different agents
running those so so so I think there's
going to be a mechanism in which we need
to learn how to more effectively use
agents but there's also like we say with
with the with the agent enablement and
the and the the drive to use context
better to get the most out of agents All
of that together will hopefully
establish a way that we can kind of like
measure how effective, how productive we
are with agents and get that kind of
start to be talking with real data, real
numbers about the ROI of us using
agents, not just individually, but as a
as a as an organization as well. Yeah,
>> I feel like I don't know if we'll get
there or not in 2026, but we'll that's I
think our mindset will shift to asking
those questions and really, you know,
performing tests that will try and give
us that data.
>> Yeah,
>> I think that's a sensible prediction.
Would you say do you think organizations
that are large enough will focus on like
getting a portion of the team to be you
know like uh five stars you know and how
they use agents more or would they focus
more on you know broadening and having
like everybody in the team use agents I
>> it's a really good question I I think
there's there's always this myth when we
think about things like um maturity that
when we look at a large organization we
think what's the maturity of this large
organization and it doesn't work like
that because every team is at a
different maturity. Every team is at a
different level of adoption. And I think
what we would what we would need to do
is recognize at what level each of these
teams are at. Some will still be in that
2025 model of that we just need to we
just need to get people using it. We
need to get into people's hands. Others
will be much much further ahead where
they'll be actually yes, these are teams
that we can actually really understand
what they're doing, how much it's
affecting them and then take those
lessons to to spread across those those
various groups. So I think there'll be a
mix to be honest.
>> Yeah. On those. Yeah. It's interesting
and I think that's very like cloud uh
adoption style or DevOps adoption style
which is you have to have some
forerunners. Uh and I think once you
demonstrate something is sort of
successful then then you start getting
excited about rolling it out to the
team.
>> Yeah. And I and I think it's equally
what we saw at sneak when we think about
developer adoption of security or
security development. It's something
that individuals have that passion for
or individual teams uh will do more
successfully and those learnings they
can be shared across to other teams
through through the value I guess.
>> Um yeah my other is I guess when we
think about last year we were talking
about model winners this year we're
actually talking about agents and will
there be a clear standout agent winner.
I think claude code today has been one
of the most successful possibly one of
the leading uh uh agentic coding uh
tools for a for a developer to use. I
think we'll see other other agents get
closer and you'll probably start seeing
that more more that kind of like you
know one model one one agent jumping
another and hopefully we I think we'll
see you because it's important for
competition that we will see that kind
of swapping and changing of this new
this new uh vendor or or existing vendor
has just added these new features and
they're actually you know more
performant than these others. I'd like
to think there are going to be some new
uh vendors that we haven't seen today um
but but we'll see. Yeah, I had a similar
one kind of in my queue which was I
think there's going to be a bit of a
separation from the between the agent
and the model. Yeah. uh uh and so you
know kind of like when you're using you
know an IDE but you use the same IDE for
developing in different languages you
know do you uh you know what what would
be the dominant uh version you know of
it would you use you know claude code so
today many of the agents support many
models you can use claude with a
non-anthropic model uh but it sort of
feels like my kind of intuition would be
like you know claude would be best with
the clawed models right like you know
with the sort of the anthropic models
and I think that's true for all the
assump ions, you know, would there be uh
independent agents that that uh work
well? Uh and so it's interesting. I
mean, I would I would predict that in
2026 there will be uh uh kind of a
increased adoption or sort of like the
rise of uh agents that are separate from
model companies uh from it or maybe an
open sourcing that sort of you know gets
contributed you know I guess goose is
one example of that. So I guess I I
would still predict that the majority of
users will use things that just sort of
come bundled in with model and agent,
you know, allin-one, but that they will
we will have some sort of sweetheart
sort of agents that uh that get adoption
that are that are separate. So we'll
see. We'll see how it goes.
>> No, I think I think that's absolutely
right. And I think we'll we'll today we
we look at an agent and we just think
it's it's yeah the agent is my AI tool
my very similar to an LLM and a lot of
people that I've spoken with sometimes
you know it's a little bit blurry the
lines between an agent and
>> there is we should note that there are a
bunch of tools today that are kind of
agent orchestrators right they're uh and
they work at higher level so you have
you know companies like uh I know like
warp or uh like warp dev in the terminal
or uh you know there are a bunch of sort
of uh agents today that are not from the
model companies. So, we'll see how they
fare.
>> Yeah,
>> I guess I would I would add to that. Um
I think your sort of comment on
uh on kind of becoming effective uh
resonates with me. Uh I I'd be more
specific and I'd say uh there will be a
whole kind of wave of best practices and
and tools and such to go from single
player to multiplayer. uh because I
think today still you know so much
development happens like in the AI the
AI native developers they're solos you
know they're sort of solo developers
maybe at most two you know they work
with a lot of alignment uh and I think
in part that's the sort of the magic
right if you think it's almost if you
think of them as managers now right
because they have teams that they
operate and so they can manage multiples
but we still need to think about
organizational alignment you know there
still needs to be you know dependencies
between one system and another and so I
think this notion of single player to
multiplayer thinking about dependencies,
thinking about commitments, you know,
how do we interact with those and how do
we still maintain the kind of the AI
native uh future. I think I think we're
going to see a lot of evolution over
there and some of that will come to the
models. I think the models might
introduce things like like committed
behavior sort of maybe introduce more
harder tests that are built in uh uh
which again you can technically do today
but often times the the agents would
just modify the tests you know to uh uh
and so practices around it. So I think
we're going to see big improvement over
there. Talked about sort of the agent uh
separation from the model. Uh clearly
you know I think agent enablement
capabilities will sort of come along
with that as well. Um and I guess we the
the one that I would sort of say that's
a bit more on the limb is I think we'll
see much more adoption of open models. I
feel like what has happened uh during uh
during this year towards the end of the
year is there are state-of-the-art
models but the the pace of change is is
reducing. you know it is shrinking and I
think there are there have been more and
more really good open models and as
enterprises and organizations as a whole
start uh kind of being more successful
with agents they will start spending a
lot of money and you know the the
immediate spend might be very worthwhile
because it it comes at the expense of
human labor which is even more expensive
but it's still big numbers and so I
think people will start getting to uh to
to really care about well like do I need
>> opus you know for this right or even
sonnet or can I just use this much much
much cheaper open model to run I think
Nvidia's acquisition of gro is like
slightly in that domain as well is like
to see see that trend happening and so I
would predict that in 2026 we'll see
much more substantial use of open models
>> uh especially especially in development
and in sort of recurring uh recurring
activities like when you're when you're
in your desktop with a model you want
you want kind of maximum power because
you know you want to work them but when
they are repeated tasks that you can
evaluate you can sort of get a sense for
how good would an open model be at that
>> comes back a little bit to that sort of
sense that like benchmarks will continue
and people will have their evaluations
>> and also the focus on effectiveness and
the ROI of what we're doing and what
we're using which
>> and I and I I think we will sort of see
a whole like one sort of stream that's
probably going to stay the minority of
people that are fully open right they're
using an open agent with an open model
uh and uh you know they're running it
you know on on sort of hosted servers
maybe but like on on sort of their
control servers uh and they run with
those because I think at this point a
lot of the accomplishment you know a lot
of the the means of success is the
methodology of how do you use the agent
how do you uh um kind of give it the
right context at the right time you know
how do you make all those interactions
and I think a lot of that knowhow will
the the the intelligence that are in the
open models uh will be will be enough to
do a lot of that work.
>> Yeah, very interesting. And we'll we'll
chat about this in 2027, which sounds
weird to say, but we have to get used to
>> barely 2026, right? [laughter] Like hold
on there, Simon. Sorry. One year at a
time. One year at a time.
>> We'll see how inaccurate we we are with
those predictions in a year's time.
We'll still be here uh with hopefully
some amazing speakers and content uh
every week at the end.
>> We have a few we already know of. Uh we
have you've already you've already
started with a couple.
>> Yeah, we're there. The beauty of
recorded podcast that we actually have a
couple of episodes coming your way you
know one with the uh previous CEO of
GitHub Thomas
uh and uh and he you know we had a great
conversation talking about a variety of
like building AI dev tools on it and
perspectives on it and you know why in
the world would we he go off and sort of
build a another AI uh dev startup on it.
Uh so that was a fun conversation and
then uh Mirao who is the CEO and founder
of D-Zero which is a really interesting
company in the observability space
talking a lot about sort of agents in
that world what is AI native for
observability uh and how do we how do we
sort of bring in that um kind of a power
of intelligence as well as like what
context is needed uh to the world of
operations which is often kind of six
determin I don't know if six determinism
because they sort of use the system
misbehaving but uh uh but it's a bit
more sort of uh um riskaware uh shall we
say. So super interesting conversations
and just the harbingers of a uh a super
interesting year with you know
>> I don't know it's probably going to be a
fairly tame year sort of a quiet year.
Yeah, I expect so. Quiet, slow moving.
>> I think it's going to make 2025 feel
quiet.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So,
>> amazing. Well, uh, all the best for for
for 2026 to everyone. A happy new year
>> and thank you for listening and uh and
following this and again, keep the uh
keep the feedback flowing.
>> Absolutely. Thanks all for listening and
tune in to the next episode.